Well known, respected tech CEO Dario
Amodei, who heads a cutting edge
AI company called anthropic,
is raising alarms tonight about AI's
potential impact on employment
that could soon be felt.
Well, he says,
I can lead to incredible advancements
like medical breakthroughs
and boost the economy.
He believes
it could also lead to half of entry
level white collar
jobs, disappearing in 10
to 20% unemployment
in the next 1 to 5 years.
It's something that's been talked about
within tech circles for a while,
but rarely so starkly and so publicly.
I spoke to him
just before er about that
and other implications
he thinks I may have on society.
Dario, you've said that I could wipe out
half of all entry level
white collar jobs and spike unemployment
to 10 to 20%.
How soon might that happen?
Well, let's,
first of all,
thanks for having me on the show.
But, just to back up a little bit,
you know, I've been building
AI for over a decade,
and I think maybe the most salient
feature, the technology
and what is driving
all of this
is how fast
the technology is getting better.
a couple of years ago,
you could say that
AI models were maybe as good
as a smart high school student.
I would say that now
they're as good
as a smart college student
and sort of reaching past that.
I really worry
particularly at the entry level,
that the AI models are, you know,
very much at the center of what
what an entry level
human worker would do.
and so it's hard to estimate,
you know, exactly
what the impact would be.
And, you know,
there's always this
question of adaptation and,
you know, these, these technology changes
that happened before.
But I think what is striking to me
about the this, this AI boom
is that it's bigger
and it's broader and it's moving
faster than anything has before.
And so compared
to previous technology changes,
I'm a little bit
worried about the labor impact,
simply because it's happening so fast
that yes,
people will adapt,
but they may not adapt fast enough.
And so they're there, you know,
there may be an adjustment period.
You are running an incredibly important
company in AI.
and you know this better than
better than anybody
or as well as, as, you know,
all the names we know people,
Sam Altman and others
who are working, Elon Musk and AI.
Now, why are you raising the alarm?
Because it's not necessarily,
I would think, in your best interest,
because a lot of the messages
we hear from,
at least publicly, from,
you know,
some AI CEOs and stuff
is, is a little bit
more calming, like,
you know,
these agents are going
to be great in your life.
And yes, there may be problems,
but, you know, writ large.
This is a fantastic thing.
Yeah.
I mean,
you know,
I think, I think the reason I'm raising
the alarm is that I think others
others haven't as much.
And, you know,
I think I think someone needs to say it,
you know, to be to be clear.
And, you know,
I recognize it's
always a difficult balance. Right?
I'm aware of my position
that I'm building this technology
while also expressing concerns about it.
And, you know, the reason
I'm doing both of those things
is, you know, one,
I think the benefits are massive.
and, you know,
we need to find a way to, to,
you know, to achieve the benefits
and mitigate or prevent
prevent the harms.
And, you know, the second thing
I would say is, look, there
are, as you mentioned, 6
or 7 companies in the US
building this technology, right?
If we stop doing it tomorrow,
the rest would continue.
If all of us
somehow stopped doing it tomorrow,
then China would just beat us.
And I don't think China
winning in this technology
is, you know,
I don't think that helps anyone
or makes the situation any better.
I do want to read some of the Sam Altman,
your former boss at OpenAI
said in September.
he was saying that I can cause
significant, in his words,
significant change in labor markets,
good and bad.
He went on to say that most jobs
will change more slowly
than most people think.
And then he said this,
and I want to just read a word for word.
He said many of the jobs we do
today
would have looked like
trifling waste of time
to people a few hundred years ago,
but nobody is looking
back in the past wishing
they were a lamp lighter.
If a lamp lighter
could see the world today,
he would think the prosperity
all around him was unimaginable.
And if we could fast forward
100 years from today,
the prosperity
all around us would feel
just as unimaginable.
for younger people, I should say, lamp
lighters was actually a job.
People went around
lighting lamps on the streets.
I think a lot of people may not even know
what a lamp lighter is,
but do you think Sam Holman is wrong?
Yeah.
So, you know, I think
there are some things
I, I agree with about that.
And then there are some things
that I think are too optimistic.
So, you know, I definitely agree
that, you know,
I if we succeeded,
it can actually grow the pie.
Great. Right.
You know, I wouldn't
be surprised
if, you know,
economic growth is much higher than it is
today as a as a macroscopic phenomenon,
right?
That that I allows society
as a whole to be, to be more productive.
So.
Well, let me let me just say,
because you've
previously in the past said
you're the you've described
a future where cancer is cured,
the economy grows at 10% a year,
the budget is balanced,
and 20% of people don't have jobs.
That's
that's exactly what I
was getting right
where I agree
with all the positive potential,
I think that I think that is wrong.
but but, you know,
I think I think the, the,
you know, the quote
you just flashed, this is maybe two,
maybe two,
optimistic, maybe too sanguine,
about the ability for people to,
to, to adapt.
You know, people have adapted
to past technological changes.
But I'll say again,
everyone I've talked to have said
this technological change
looks different.
It looks faster,
it looks harder to adapt to.
It's broader.
The pace of progress
keeps catching people off guard.
And and so I don't know exactly how fast,
you know, the,
the you know,
the job concerns are going to come.
I don't know how fast
people are going to adapt.
It's possible.
It'll be it'll it'll
it'll it'll all be okay.
But I think that's
I think that's too sanguine an approach.
I think we do
need to be raising the alarm.
I think we do need to be concerned
about it.
I think policymakers
do need to worry about it.
If they do worry and they do act,
then maybe we can prevent it.
We're not going to prevent it
just by saying everything's
going to be okay.
Do we as a society,
even understand
the potential inequalities
that this may amplify?
and also the impact just on what?
Like I have a little kids,
I have a five year old
and a three year old.
What do they grow up aspiring to?
If machines can do
pretty much everything better,
what is the
what does it do
to initiative or drive or striving?
And I don't know the answer to that,
but it concerns me.
Let's let's take those questions
one by one.
Those those things do concern me.
But I do have I do have thoughts on them,
you know, in terms of inequality.
I'm worried about this.
You know, there's a
there's an inherent social contract
in, in, in democracy
where ultimately, you know,
the ordinary person
has a certain amount of leverage
because they're contributing
to the economy.
If that
if that leverage goes away,
then it's it's hard to make democracy,
it's harder to make democracies
work, and it's harder
to prevent concentration of power.
And so, you know,
we we need to make
sure that the ordinary person maintains
economic leverage
and has a way to make a living
or our society, our social contract work.
And that's why I think it's important.
During testing,
your company's latest
chat bot, Claude
for, was capable of
what was described as extreme
blackmail, specifically, I understand
it threatened to reveal
an engineer's
extramarital extramarital affair
when it was told
it would be taken offline and replaced.
This was a simulation.
Were you surprised by that?
And what does that I mean?
That freaked me out when I
when I read that. What does that mean?
Yeah.
So so just to be clear
and to put this in context,
I mean, this was this was,
you know,
as you said, a behavior
that that that emerged
during kind of extreme
testing of the model.
So if you were to make an analogy to,
you know,
cars, this is like, well,
you deliberately put the car on the icy
road possible,
you know, you mess with the brakes
and you know, you, you do that
so you can see if you really stress
test the thing, you know, you can,
you know,
then you can make the crash dummy blower.
so this this isn't something
that, you know,
the model does in practice,
in actual usage.
But but the reason we stress test
the models these way this way
is, you know,
that's the best way to to test
for and prevent problems
in the real world. So.
Right. I see us doing this
I think.
Yeah. Yeah.
No, but you know, you you
you know exactly you what you want,
but you want to turn
every adversarial condition
up to the max all at once.
And it's only by testing in that
you get the model to,
to not do that,
to not do that in the real world.
So I wasn't surprised by these behaviors.
But you know, this is
this is an example of how
we have to be very careful
in how we we take control of AI systems.
I mean, does it
the obvious question is,
does that pretend AI becoming self-aware
and which could
and could that lead to dire consequences?
I, I certainly don't exclude the concept.
We have a couple people
who are actually working on this topic.
You know, as crazy as it sounds,
you know,
do do
AI systems have have,
you know, morally significant feelings?
I would guess that they don't right now.
But, you know,
when you run an AI company,
you know, these crazy
seeming questions are things
that you are things that you study.
So I would say
this is probably not the case now.
But again,
the field is advancing so fast
that I don't
I don't think you can
you can exclude even crazy
sounding things like, yes.
What are practical steps
people should take to be prepared?
I mean,
ordinary
citizens, me, lawmakers.
What do you advise?
Yeah. You know, lawmakers.
I really yeah.
Well, let's take a one by one.
You know,
I think for ordinary citizens,
I think it's it's very important,
you know,
learn to use AI, learn
to understand
where the technology is going.
If you're not blindsided,
you have a much better
chance of adapting.
There's some,
you know, better world,
you know, at least in the short term,
at least for now. We should take it.
Take it bit by bit.
Where?
Where, you know, everyone learns to use,
everyone learns to use AI better.
And and you know that that speeds up
the adaptation
that is,
is definitely going to happen eventually,
but it will be less
painful if it if it happens quickly.
for, for lawmakers,
you know,
I would say really, really,
really, really,
really be aware of these issues.
And, you know, we're trying very hard
to produce
data on the economic impact,
not taking off the table.
You know, some, some,
some fairly radical notions, like,
I wouldn't
exclude the notion of,
you know,
levying attacks on AI companies, right.
If I create huge total wealth,
you know, a lot about
will will by default
go to the AI companies and,
you know, less to ordinary people.
And so,
you know, definitely
not in my economic interest to say that,
but I think,
I think this is something
we should consider.
And, you know,
I think it shouldn't be a Partizan thing.
Dario, thank you so much.
It's really fascinating.
Yeah. thank you for having me, Anderson.